<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>A testimony in that which separates between the pretious [sic] and the vile and is for the friends and brethren who love the Lord Lesus [sic] Christ in sincerity and truth.</title>
            <author>Bolton, John, 1599-1679.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1677</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 28 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 7 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2012-10">2012-10 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A28617</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing B3510</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R29046</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">10802253</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 10802253</idno>
            <idno type="VID">45963</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A28617)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 45963)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 1416:11)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>A testimony in that which separates between the pretious [sic] and the vile and is for the friends and brethren who love the Lord Lesus [sic] Christ in sincerity and truth.</title>
                  <author>Bolton, John, 1599-1679.</author>
                  <author>Fox, George, 1624-1691.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>10, 3 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>s.n.,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>[London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1673]</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Caption title.</note>
                  <note>Signed on p. 10: J.B.</note>
                  <note>A postscript signed: G.F. (George Fox)</note>
                  <note>Imprint suggested by Wing.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in the Harvard University Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Society of Friends --  Pastoral letters and charges.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2009-09</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-10</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-08</date>
            <label>Ali Jakobson</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-08</date>
            <label>Ali Jakobson</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-05</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb facs="tcp:45963:1"/>
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:45963:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <head>A Teſtimony in that which ſeparates between the preti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous and the vile. And is for the friends and brethren who love the lord Ieſus Chriſt in ſincerity and truth.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">L</seg>Et it not ſeem as a ſtrange thing to my friends and brethen, that any thing of this nature ſhould come forth from me, for I have a teſtimony in my heart from the living God, that it is in unfeigned love to the Everlaſting Truth, which we recieved in the beginning, and am clear in this matter before the Lord who ſearcheth the heart and tryeth the Reines. That I have been very often in fear, leaſt that pretious Truth of the living God that we received in the beginning with gladneſs of heart ſhould by the ſubtilty of the Enemie if poſſible be made void; (which could never be) who hath been very reſtleſs and hath left no means unattempted either for the overthrowing the truth and righteouſneſs of God, or the undermining of it; that ſo the bleſſed Truth of God, might not take place in the hearts of the ſonns of men; ſurely ſtrong cryes have been put up to the Lord, that the Enemie of the Soul might never be able to hinder or ſtop the breaking forth of the Goſpel of Peace, which hath again been publiſhed in our Age; and our Eyes have beheld the glory thereof; bleſſed be the name of God for ever. To you my breth<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ren that are ſo in the truth, I can freely open my heart and declare the
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:45963:2"/> State of my mind to; It is now about fiveteen or ſixteen Months ſince the Lord called for this ſervice and teſtimonie from me; and there was in me a very great deal of backwardneſs to it, and a fear in me leaſt I ſhould do hurt in this matter, and ſtill when I laid it by, the Lord in ſome further appearance in his light, calls for the teſtimony that he had made to appear within, muſt be brought forth for his names ſake, and in this matter I have lingred long till almoſt as in the judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of ſome now almoſt if not altogether to late, yet as the mercies of the Lord have been very great to give many fatherly admonitions, and yet to ſpare ſo not only now to accept, but alſo as at the beginning to call for it, in this my wittneſs for Gods pretious truth, what ever my words are, yet no touch of bitterneſs in my Spirit againſt any mans per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon but a true love to all, that there may be a returning by them that have erred from the ſtraight way to the pure path of life. The teſtimony that God called for was, that notwithſtanding I had profeſt his name and ſuffered many things, for bearing witneſs to the Goſpel of Salvation. Yet that which he now required was; that I muſt leave my witneſs a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mongſt my freinds and brethren, for the everlaſting and unchangeable truth of the pure God, that whenſoever the Lord ſhould remove me out of this houſe of clay, and take me more fully into the boſome of Eternal reſt, that this may ſignifie unto as many as ſhall come to read theſe few lines, what is the ground and cauſe, which I and all the faithfull breth<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ren and friends have ſo deeply ſuffered for, many in our own Country and ſome in forraigne parts. Which ſuffering of his choſen ones al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>though deſpiſed and perſecuted in this Generation, yet God hath a tender reſpect to, and it will be more manifeſt in due time. My truely beloved brethren and friends I have in the diligence of my ſoul weighed and conſidered, as concerning that Truth which we received in the be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ginning, which we have ſo earneſtly contended for, and that with ſo much hazard and danger even the loſs of outward eſtate and liberty, and the life of the natural man, and whatſoever elſe may be dear unto us in this preſent world; Yet not to uſe many words in this caſe but ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther few and alſo plainneſs of ſpeech, becauſe I find our cauſe our wit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs and teſtimony in this our generation to be very weighty and of ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceeding
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:45963:2"/> g<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>eat concern, in as much as it concerns the Truth of God in this world. And although our tryalls and ſufferings have been very great, yet at this time they need not be reckoned up, becauſe the ſuffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rings and hardſhips we have undergone for the Truth, or in the pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent generation &amp; ſo are freſh in memory &amp; we yet feel the ſo art of them, and what we may yet further undergo for the ſame cauſe; we freely leave it to our God, from whom our ſtrength is; and in weighing the thing before the Lord, what it was at the firſt that ſo engaged us to ſuffer and what we received that made us in the patience, and meekneſs to und<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>rgo, what was laid on us by the Enemie, this An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwer aroſe from the Lord in my heart; the truth as it is in <hi>Christ Jeſus</hi> and in the word, there was and is a ſoul ſatisfying fullneſs. Then I conſidered further in my ſelf how it was the Truth as it was in <hi>Jeſus Chriſt,</hi> and the word further was that which never changeth. Now my dear friends and Brethren was it not ſo that in the beginning we did in Truth receive the truth as it is in <hi>Jeſus Chriſt,</hi> bleſſed be God you are not ignorant of it, that we received the Truth in the love of it, as it was in the Everlaſting light of Gods power, and the way thereof is known, and a ſtranger to it cannot intermeddle with our Joy let his words be what ever they will, and the Truth hath been further made known to us by the effects of it; and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore I ſhall ſpeake a few words to you, whom God hath called and raiſed up by his living power, in the preſent generation, to beare witneſs to his holy name, it is not only freſh in my memory, but I feel the vertue of it ſtill (bleſſed be the Lord God for ever) how the Truth as it is in <hi>Jeſus,</hi> at the firſt more abundanly then ever we knew before opened our hearts to God, and he by his living power hath kept them ſo that the Enemie with all the hard uſage and grievous per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſecutions (which we have undergone) could never yet be able to ſtop the ſprings of life in us, and did it not revive our very ſouls, and it was indeed a true tranſlation from death to life, and ſo we came to know what the true Love of the brethren was, ſurely it was ſo at that day, we were (mark that) joyned to the Lord in the Covenant of light, in which our fellowſhip with the father, and the ſonne is, and
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:45963:3"/> one with another; you that have kept your integrity to the living God, and his pretious (marke that) unchangeable Truth, how was it with us in the day, when we gave up our names to the Lord to be his, with what we were, and had in this preſent world, did not the Lord gain into himſelf a full conſent with the whole mind to be Gods, and not our own, and to give up for his names ſake, All that was dear to us in this preſent World, you that know the truth and the firſt love and alſo kept your habitations in the Everlaſting and un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>changeable light of the pure God, and love a dwelling place therein: I can ſay with you, and it hath been often with me (when I have been alone as to man) although perſecuted in this world, to Conclude in my ſoul in a ſettled iudgement, my lot with yours was fallen to us in a good place, and whatſoever the Enemie can, or God ſhall permit him to be able to do to us abiding in the Truth that never changeth, yet ſtill to keep our habitation, and as God in his Everlaſting mercy hath choſen us to be heirs of the inheritance which is incorruptible, and fadeth not away, ſo hath he made us willing to undergo, what<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoever the Enemie ſhall be further able to lay on us: Now my dear friends and brethren I was not perſwaded in my mind that the bare teſtimony of the Truth of the living God, would be unpleaſing to any amongſt us, but that which appeared ſo to me is yet behind and that is in ſhort, it is ſo. God bears teſtimony in my heart by his Spirit whom my ſoul loves, becauſe its holy, but as he called me to bear witneſs to the Truth as it is in <hi>Jeſus Christ</hi> that never changeth, ſo alſo he called me to teſtifie, and to leave my witneſs for God, in this way, againſt the falſe and deceivable Spirits that is crept in amongſt us; you are not ignorant that after we had received the Truth, as it is in <hi>Jeſus Chriſt</hi> in the Love of it; in the firſt publication of it in <hi>London,</hi> that within a ſhort time after how the Divell in an in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrument fitted for that purpoſe, begun to ſow tares, and to bring in that which did not gather to <hi>Chriſt</hi> the true light, but did and was a means to ſcatter abroad, as it appears to this day, and it is needfull for the ſake of the ſimple hearted ot ſay ſomething as to that appearance of the Enemy amongſt us the Lambs of <hi>Christ</hi> that were newly brought
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:45963:3"/> forth to God and were of a harmleſs Nature, who knew little more as to a ſettled iudgment, but only the heart melted and truely broken before the living God which in that day was accounted of great eſteem amongſt us, then came forth the Enemie in the ſpirit of Exaltation, and what for? but to draw diſciples after him, as in that day I heard it ſaid by him; my Father will give me a People out of you but he Lord God who is rich in mercy, and full of Compaſſion to all that in Truth of heart depend upon him, preſerved a People to himſelf in that day, and kept them chaſte in their hearts to the living God, who made a full diſcovery of the wiles of the Enemy of the ſoul in that appearance; and ſhame and confuſion came upon all thoſe that were gathered into it. But my dear friends the Enemy retains his old Nature ſtill, he goes up and down ſeeking whom he may devoure, therefore if he appear as an Angel of light, let his form of words be whatſoever they will, we who have a habitation in the pure light of <hi>Jeſus Chriſt,</hi> whom God hath manifeſted his mercy to whereby we are preſerved in our firſt love to God and his Everlaſting pretiuos Truth; ſurely it makes the Truth as it is in <hi>Jeſus Christ,</hi> exceeding precious to all that fear and love the Lord, in ſincerity of heart. The Enemy of the ſoul (as I ſaid before in his firſt appearance from a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mongſt our ſelves after we had received the light, and the good old way that whoſoever walks in it finds reſt to the ſoul) in the Spirit of exal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tation lifting up himſelf, yet is manifeſt to be of another ſeed then the ſeed of <hi>Abraham.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>When God had overturned the work of the Enemy in that appea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rance, and ſufficienly laid him open not only to the friends of God amongſt our ſelves, but alſo to all ſober people in the Nation that had heard thereof. Soon after this, the Enemy whoſe work it is to go up and downe, ſeeking whom he may devoure, deing diſappointed as I ſaid in that appearance, now takes another forme to himſelf, and now manifeſtly appears to be of that ſeed whom God hath curſed, in tempting Eve to eat of the forbidden fruit, and in this Appearance the Serpent comes out in part like himſelf, and ſayes I am a Worme, a Creeping thing the leaſt of Creeping things, yet in his work he clear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:45963:4"/> manifeſts himſelf to be of the Serpents ſeed whoſe work it was and is to draw out from God, and from fellowſhip with them that walk in the light of God, for in the beginnning when the Truth as it is in <hi>Jeſus</hi> was preached unto us and we receiving the ſame with gladneſs of heart, what ſweet communion and fellowſhip had we together in the Spirit of holineſs, and in that day the Spirituall Iſrael of God, were as a flock that came out from the washing, prepared in heart by God to be a living ſacrifice to the Lord and to walk in the good old way which is the light in which the fellowſhip is with the Father, and with the ſon and one with another. And I teſtifie for the Lord in that day we knew no jarr or diviſion amongſt us, but our ſouls prefer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red a living in the truth above all earthly things; and this I can ſay the Truth (as it is in <hi>Jeſus Chriſt</hi>) is not leſſe beautifull now then it was in the beginning although we have been deeply tryed in our teſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mony for the living God, and after a true clear ſettlement of the friends of God, in the Everlaſting light of holineſs, into which they had been gathered and where they ſtand not to be tempted neither by preferment in this World nor eaſe to the fleſh, nor any other thing whatſoever, from the love to or walking in the Truth as it is in <hi>Jeſus,</hi> then as I ſaid before comes forth the Enemy in the ſecond appearance, creeping on his belly, but ſtill to deceive and draw from the ſimplicity of the Goſpel, but the Lord God Everlaſting that ever is a near Rock of refuge to all that depend upon him, who have no other helper on the Earth, he is rich in mercy, and his Compaſſions fail not, I teſtify it is ſo. And what ſaith he of this creeping thing; the word of Truth to me was, It is a ſelf ſeeking and a ſelf ſeparating Spirit; And what was the glory that this Spirit would have drawn us to? and which he was moved as he ſaid,<note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>s not <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>s the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ound of <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>viſion <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ongſt</note> when he was in Rome to lay before friends in <hi>England</hi> and elſe where, this was the mighty matter, that was to be brought forth by it, to keep on the hat in prayer to God, and the ground and reaſon was becauſe the Church of Rome in their traditional Worſhip in the fall did keep of their hats in prayer, And while this Spirit would be pleading ſeem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ingly againſt the practice of the Church of Rome, would in the mean
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:45963:4"/> time ſtrike at the very life of <hi>Chriſt,</hi> into which (let it never be for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gotten by us) we were brought and this was the heavenly place, which we were ſet down in, glory honor and praiſe be to God ſaith my ſoul for ever. But in this the Enemy bleſſed be God, was diſappointed (marke that) in all them that love and fear the name of the living God; And when that could not take effect, but the creeping thing was diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>covered to be an Enemy to the pretious life by them that were upon their watch Tower &amp; were gathred out of all Romiſh Traditions to <hi>Chriſt</hi> the true light, that lighteth every man that cometh into the World; but the Enemy he is reſtleſs ſtill, and ſince he hath gotten ſome diſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ples in his firſt attempt, but what ſaith my God of them (It muſt be borne I ſay ſince it is the will of my heavenly father) they are wandring ſtarres, and wells without water and if they returne not to that in which the true unity and fellowſhip is with the father and the ſonne and the one with another; there will be a lamentation for them in my ſoul, and that becauſe I love and deſire the good of all men and not the hurt of any. The Enemy in the ſecond attempt laboured to breake down our hedge and fence wherein and whereby God hath compaſſed us about and made a true ſeparation between us and all thoſe that are not yet come to beleeve in the true light, for that which ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>parates us from the World is that which we have owned (Marke that) in the ſight of Nations and which we have ſo deeply ſuffered for in our own Country and from our neighbours and kindred according to the fleſh, is it for any thing elſe, but that the light, Spirit and power of <hi>Christ</hi> might not only take place in our hearts for a time, but alſo bear rule in us and over us for ever. But the Serpent that creeps on his belly he would pluck up our fence and lay us in common again with the World (which he can never do for it is upon the root) and take away our Crowne (which is to live to God by virtue of his power) and that by writing an epiſtle for the moſt pure unity and amitie, and the taking away the hedge of Opinions as is there expreſt, And what is it that this creeping thing counts the Quakers hedge that is but an o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pinion that ſeparates us from others? truely I know nothing but the light, and power of the living God, and if the creeping thing could
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:45963:5"/> robor take away this pretious pearle from us which we have ſold all for, and yet there is no repenting in our hearts that we have ſo done, &amp; that becauſe the light &amp; power of the living God hath woonn our hearts to fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low God as dear children, &amp; not to return to this preſent World, but the Serpent that creeps on his belly, &amp; duſt is his meat he would bring us, who are as the firſt fruits unto God into conformity unto this preſent World, and if the Sects of wich he ſpeaks that are but yet in the opini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons will come over to us &amp; beleeve in the light, that they may be made par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>takers of the Power of the living God, which only can deliver from ſin, then they together with us may partake of fellowſhip with the Father and with the ſonne, for till People come to that truely, they cannot have fellowſhip with us in the things of our God, let the Serpent doe what ever he will and bleſſed be God we are not of them that are given to change and toſſed about with every wind of doctrine, it is ſo my heart reioyceth in it for ever, there are by the grace of God, that are eſtabliſhed upon the rock of Ages let what creeping thing ſoever, under never ſo faire pretences Come forth, neither the inſtrument of the evil one under colour of a higher diſpenſation, we look not for another; for I can ſay and ſpeak the truth in Chriſt and lye not that my heart together with yours is fixt and not to be removed no not by perſecution of the Ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mie without us Although they have nothing juſtly to charge againſt us, unleſſe a good Converſation from the hope that we have in Chriſt, the true light that lighteth every man that Cometh into the World neither by thoſe Enemies for ſo they are that are gon out from us, and truely were never of us, in as much as there ſtill is a diſſenting ſpirit Maintained even to this day, and that from the ground of diviſion in the keeping on the hat in prayer to God which cleerly manifeſts that there is not a unity (mark that) in the true root, for this was the glory of the Antient ſpouſe of <hi>Chriſt</hi> in the dayes of the Apoſtles, they had one Lord that ruled over them, one hope that was in them, one faith, one Spirit, into which they were baptized, and being built upon the true rock and perfectly Joyned toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:45963:5"/> to be a holy habitation for the living God to dwell in. And friends what is there in that Spirit that ſtands in the diviſion that is not in the unity in the comely order, and in the unity in the body, I teſtifie for the Lord this day I cannot, I dare not keep it back; It is the old Ran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting Spirit that was in Mildred and others that roſe up a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt Friends and truth in the dayes of <hi>J. N.</hi> and as then called by the Lord to bear my teſtimony for him and againſt that Spirit, ſoe hath the Lord called me to bear witneſs for the Truth againſt this (mark) that which is but one in the ground with the former, and to you who are of an upright heart, who love the unchangeable Truth of the living God, and are not given to change, but a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bides in the living vine, for unleſs I and you<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> continue in him, we as well as others cannot bring forth fruit to the living God, for I have rejoyced in all my trialls that al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>though mocked and ſcorned, and as a fool in this World, yet it is for <hi>Christ</hi> the Power of God and the wiſdom of God, for it is ſo, we are by him brought to Mount Zyon that cannot be moved, we come to know that ſcripture ful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>filled in us and to us, he will keep him in perfect peace whoſe mind is ſtaid on him, and you my friends who are friends of God, and whom God hath magnified his mercy to, in calling of you, out of the World and bringing of you neer to himſelf and in making of you veſſels of honour, fitted by him for his Maſters uſe, You that have been faithfull in your teſtimony for God in the day of tryall and have not joyned with the Enemy that hath riſen up from among our ſelves, whereby your ſtrength in the living teſtimony was not abaited to you, I ſpeak al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>though but a Babe in him, yet one that is brought forth by the heavenly father in the Everlaſting and unchangeable light to live and die with you, your faces have been plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſant to behold, but the degenerate Spirit, that which took
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:45963:6"/> occaſion and forſook the Aſſemblys of the Saints under what pretence ſoever, as alſo that ſpirit, that is a ſelf ſeeking, ſelfe ſeparating Spirit that under pretence of being moved, and thereby laid a ground of diviſion amongſt them whoſe faces were turned towards Zyon; The teſtimony that is gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven me to bear and leave behind me, when I ſhall be no more, (as to that which is Mortall) is I have no part with them, and you who are dear in the ſight of the Lord, this I have to ſay to you, I am often comforted when in the retiredneſs of my mind I am more with him who is the life, that God will lift up and exalt the dominion of <hi>Jeſus Chriſt</hi> over all that which is contrary amongſt us, and the Truth as it is in him, that never changed but abides the ſame for ever ſhall remain and continue.</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>J. B.</signed>
            </closer>
            <trailer>THE END.</trailer>
         </div>
         <div type="postscript">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:45963:6"/>
            <head>A Poſtſcript.</head>
            <p>THe power of the Lord God is over all them that keep on their hats in prayer, and they do not keep on their hats in pray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er neither by motion, power of God, nor by the Spirit of God, but (by an earthly dark Spirit) againſt it, and them that be in the power of God: This was the firſt Ground of it both in <hi>Jo. Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rot,</hi> and his Company, when he run out, and <hi>J. N.</hi> when he run out; and this firſt it was done in oppoſition to them that was in the Truth, and in the power of God; but the power of God will cruſh to pieces that fained dark earthly Spirit, to pieces, and to the earth and pit it muſt go, with all its fained and falſe preten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces; and the power of the Lord God, and his Truth, reigns over it all.</p>
            <p>The firſt that got up into this poſture of keeping on their hats in prayer againſt friends, was the Ranters; the next was <hi>J. N.</hi> but he quickly, by the power of the Lord, ſaw it, and judged it; and the next was <hi>Jo. Perrot,</hi> whoſe end was according to his work, and ſo will thoſe that continue in it; for the power of God is over them, and their dark earthly Spirit; and the power of God was before they were, and will remain when that they be gone, and it reigns: and this is the word of the Lord God to you all. And for my part I had as leive to ſee a Prieſt to ſtand up in a Meeting, as one of theſe dark earthly Spirits, with their hats on their heads, when that friends pray, for they cannot deceive friends. For I have been more burthened with their dark, ſubtle and ſophiſters Spirit, than with the Prieſts, which had no more ſhew of reverence to God (in that) than to a horſe; whoſe outward ſeeming righteouſneſs hath deceived many: but the power of God, (which deſtroyeth the deceiver) undeceiveth and bring<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth people to that which did firſt convince them. And them that kept on their hats when friends prayed, after a while ſome of
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:45963:7"/> them ran to the Prieſts to be married, and ſome to hear them in the Steeple-houſes, then this dark earthly Spirit could bow, and put off its hat to its own; the dark Spirit which kept on the hat in the aſſemblies of the righteous, in oppoſition againſt the Spirit and power of God: And ſo this Spirit hath led people into a feigned<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, and love, and liberty, which the power and Spirit of God cannot own, but judge, and ſtand over, and reign over, if they keep their habitations in the power, and life, and truth of God which reigneth.</p>
            <p>If they that are and have been in this dark earthly Spirit, had but had a regard to the power of God, and his Truth, they would have been tender, and afraid of giving any occaſion or offence, both to them that be within, and to them that be without, to draw out their minds to look at that which their earthly Spirit has promoted; and ſo to lay ſtumbing blocks, and ſet up an Idol, and an Image to look at, which draws peoples eyes from the witneſs of God in themſelves; but the power of God is gone over it, and will break it down: And ſo this Belials Spirit, which would be wthout yoak, cryes (to ſuch as in love exhorts them, and judges it) <hi>You Lord over us:</hi> And ſo this earthly dark Spirit, (which is gotten above the witneſs of God in themſelves, which is not ſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſible of the moving Spirit and power of God) it ſets up its own earthly form, which the power of God never ſet up, but judges; And this earthly Spirit judges all that are gathered together in the power, and that are conſtained by the power and love of God, in a familiar way, to take one another by the hand, through the dearneſs and nearneſs of the love of God, and the pure, clean and holy life; and alſo are moved by the power of the Lord God to put off their hats in prayer. This dark Sophiſter, earthly Spirit, thus hath judged theſe practices of the people of God afore-mentioned, to be but a form, which are done in the power of God, it being out of the power it ſelf, and the fellowſhip and unity of it. And becauſe they that are in it, are gone (from that which firſt con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vinced them) into outward things, and into their form in the
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:45963:7"/> earthly Spirit, it judges thoſe that will not follow them that have loſt the power of God; and thus many of them are darkned with a cankered ruſty Spirit, which will corrupt them, and hath deſtroyed many: And this is that that has brought the plague of hardneſs of heart, through which there has been ſtrangeneſs, and not unity, nor familiarneſs, nor nighneſs in the Truth; for how ſhould it, when they are gone from that which firſt convinced them? To that all muſt come, before they have fellowſhip and true unity in the power and truth of God; which if that had been minded, it would have lead to follow whatſoever things are comely, whatſoever things are decent, whatſoever things are of good report, and ſuch things as make for peace: but this Spirit has followed the contrary, and therefore the power of the Lord God is againſt it, and over it gone, and reigns, and the life and truth.</p>
            <p>And you, with your earthly Spirit, and earthly form, have given occaſion to the world to ſay, that the people of God called Quakers are divided, ſome with their hats on, and ſome with them off, and ſo they are oppoſite one to the other. And this is the fruits of the earthly Spirit, which would bring darkneſs and earth over all; But the power of God is over all this dark and earthly Spirit, and the world, and them that be in it; and looketh upon them, and the world, one againſt the truth, and the power of God. And the peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple of God called Quakers, are one (and not divided) in the power of God, and his truth; and in Gods power and Spirit they are in unity in the truth and power of an endleſs life. This I was moved of the Lord God to write.</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>G. F.</signed>
            </closer>
            <trailer>The End.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
